Ivan Mrekaj

Bratislava, SK



mrekaj.ivan@gmail.com



linkedin.com/in/ivan-mrekaj

mobile: +421948033058

Summary

As an enthusiastic environmental and climate data scientist with experience in fields such as forestry, phenology, and drought monitoring. I have developed strong problem-solving and workflow development skills. I am an analytical thinker with deep interest in the interactions between the biosphere and the atmosphere passionate about understanding and addressing climate change and its impacts on ecosystems. I am confident in my ability to work independently and contribute to advancing our understanding of these complex issues.

Skills

Data Analysis • R • Python • SQL • GIS software (QGIS) • Google Earth Engine • Phenology • Problem Solving • Research • Independence

Experience

Data Analyst/Scientists

Solargis s.r.o.

Sep 2022 - present

- Conducting quality control on meteorological and solar irradiance data
- Analysing meteorological and environmental data
- Developing of an automated tool for QC of meteorological data
- · Writing technical reports

Climate and Environmental Data Scientist

Slovak Hydrometeorological Institute

Aug 2020 - Aug 2022 (2 years 0)

- Analysing and studying long-term phenological events of plants and animals
- · Spatial analysis of phenological evens and calculating the long term phenological averages
- Studying the long-term impact of drought on forest
- Analysis of climatological variables and environmental data
- Monthly and yearly reporting of phenological events

Observer and Reporter

Slovak Hydrometeorological Institute

Mar 2018 - Present (4 years +)

· Weekly observing and reporting of drought and its impact on forests and daily observing and monthly reporting phenological events of plants and animals

Project Manager

Slovak Hydrometeorological Institute

Mar 2019 - Jul 2020 (1 year 5 months)

- Managed and implemented of the project "Improving the standard of the National pollution register" and related administration
- Managed 15-people team

Specialist for Forest and Nature Protection

Forests SK

Feb 2017 - Feb 2019 (2 years 1 month)

- · Managed tasks related to nature and landscape protection, forest protection and forest health
- Managed weekly monitoring and basic yearly prediction of occurrence of harmful factors in forests
- Prepared of monthly reports and statistics, monthly and yearly analyses in the field of ecology and forest protection
- · Budgeted forest protection activities
- Coordinated 5 forest protection specialist and managed they activities related to forest protection

Assistant Project Manager

Forests SK

Jul 2017 - Jun 2018 (1 year)

• Managed and implemented of the project "Common education about beekeeping for practical application in the region Beskydy" and related administration

Forester

Forests SK

Aug 2014 - Jan 2017 (2 years 6 months)

- Weekly monitoring of the condition and development of the forest ecosystem dynamics
- · Collecting insect samples for research
- · Participation in the development of a trap for bark beetles which uses biological preparations
- Designed and implemented of cultivation technologies and procedures for the optimization of species and spatial structures, resistance, and quality of forest stands
- Designing and providing activities to maintain and enhance biological diversity
- Managed of three forestry working teams (organization, direction, assignment, and control of works)

Education

Technical University, Zvolen

- Graduate degree, Forestry
 - 2013 2015
- Undergraduate degree, Forestry 2010 - 2013

Certifications

First Aid, Forestry Pedagogy, Certificate of Professional Competence in the Field of Plant Protection

Licences & Trainings

Drivers Licence (AM, B1, B)

Online Training on Climate Services for Adaptation Using Climate Data, Wageningen University, NL 2021 Online Training in Atmospheric Composition, EUMETSAT/ESA/ECMWF, 2021

Marine Data4Med, Mercator Ocean, Copernicus, Noveltis, 2022